Finding Aid for the Helen H. Lyman Papers, circa 1890-2002 (bulk 1955-1998)
State University of New York at Buffalo. University Archives
Helen H. Lyman Papers, circa 1890-2002 (bulk 1955-1998)
45/F/1000
Lyman, Helen H., 1910-
34 manuscript boxes, 1 half box (14.40 linear feet)
State University of New York at Buffalo. University Archives
The papers of adult services librarian and library science professor, Helen Huguenor Lyman, which span almost 70 years of research and writing on the subject of adult literacy. Also includes personal writings and genealogical notes on the Huguenor family.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The Helen H. Lyman Papers, circa 1890-2002 (bulk 1955-1998), are open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received in two accessions: #00-036, American Library Association (ALA) publication manuscripts, 1954-1977, was received from Helen H. Lyman on June 2000 and #03-725 was transferred to the Archives by Lyman's nephew, Richard H. Stamps on August 28, 2003.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
1910 (March 16) Helen Lucille Huguenor born in Hornell, NY
1932 B.A., College of Arts and Sciences, University of Buffalo
1932-1952 Buffalo Public Library (now the Buffalo & Erie County Public Library)
1932-1935 Circulation Assistant
1935-1942 Co-head of the Readers' Bureau with Lucille Adams
1943-1944 Administrative Assistant
1944-1952 Head, Adult Education department
1940 B.S. Library Science, University of Buffalo
1950-1951 Instructor, "Great Books Course", Millard Fillmore College, University of Buffalo
1950-1954 Board of Directors, Great Book Foundation, Chicago, IL
1952-1953 Director, American Libraries Association (ALA), Adult Education Survey, Chicago, IL
1955-1956 Advance Study at the Graduate Library School, University of Chicago
1957-1959 Adult Services Librarian, Hild Regional Branch, Chicago Public Library
1959-1963 Public Library Consultant Specialist in Adult Services, Wisconsin Free Library Commission, Madison, WI
1964-1965 Director, Reference Department (Associate Professor), Lockwood Memorial Library, State University of New York at Buffalo
1965 Director and Consultant, Reading Guidance Institute, Library School, University of Wisconsin-Madison
1965-1967 Public Library Specialist for Adult Services, Library Services Branch, Office of Education, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Washington, DC
1966-1977 Assistant Professor (1966-1972), Associate Professor (1973-1976), Professor (1976-1977), Library School, University of Wisconsin-Madison (named Professor Emeritus in 1978)
1967-1972 Director and Principle Investigator, Research Project, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," Library School, University of Wisconsin-Madison
1969 (July 21-August 1) Director, Institute for Training in Librarianship: "Film and the Library," Library School, University of Wisconsin-Madison
1969-1970 President of Adult Services Division, American Libraries Association (ALA)
1973 Published Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader
1976 Published Reading and the Adult New Reader
1977 Published Literacy and the Nation's Libraries
1977-1998 Adjunct Professor, Library and Information Studies Program, State University of New York at Buffalo (later named Professor Emeritus)
1979 Received the Joseph W. Lippincott Award for distinguished service in the profession of librarianship, American Library Association (ALA)
1986 First recipient of the Margaret E. Monroe Library Adult Services Award for significant contributions to and an impact on library adult services, the Reference and Adult Services Division (RASD) of the American Library Association (ALA)
1987 Received the University at Buffalo Distinguished Alumni Award
2002 (November 4) died in her hometown of Orchard Park, NY
"'Her pioneering study of adult education activities in public libraries in 1954 had a catalytic impact on library adult services.' [Peter] Hiatt [Chair of the Margaret E. Monroe Library Adult Services Award Committee, 1986] noted that Lyman is closely identified with literacy programs and public libraries and is currently linking retired citizens and literacy work in new, experimental ways."
[from press release: "Lyman receives ALA/RASD Monroe library adult services award" by Deborah G. Robertson and Linda K. Wallace, June 1986]
Scope and Content Note
The Helen H. Lyman collection is divided into four series:
I is biographical and personal information that includes Lyman's genealogical work on the Huguenor family as well as the handwritten notes that was the beginnings of her autobiography, "My Life."
II is Lyman's professional work with the American Libraries Association (ALA), the Buffalo Public Library (today the Buffalo & Erie County Public Library), conferences, workshops. Also included is the Library Materials Research Project (LMRP) produced for the Office of Libraries and Learning Technologies at the U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare and many of Lyman's published works including Reading and the New Adult Reader and Adult Services: Vision and Performance.
III is Lyman's outline and syllabi for courses taught at both the University of Wisconsin-Madison Library School from 1966-1977 and the University at Buffalo, 1977-1998. Lyman was Professor Emerita at both of these institutions.
IV is collected materials and notes on gathered research in the field of adult literacy. Throughout her life, Lyman actively collected source information on different aspects of adult learning in public libraries.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series: Series I. Biographical; Series II. Professional; and Series III. Teachings.
Container List
- Biographical, I.
  - Personal, 1910, 1936-2001, I.A
    - Awards, 1951, 1979, 1982, 1986-1987, 1999; includes the Joseph W. Lippincott, the Margaret E. Monroe Library Adult Services, and the UB Distinguished Alumni Awards. (Box-folder 1.1)
    - Biographical resources, 1965, 1976-1977, 1983-1984, undated; includes ALA "Facts and Faces," Contemporary Authors, Who's Who of American Women. (Box-folder 1.2)
    - Clippings, 1910, circa 1940-circa 1995 (Box-folder 1.3)
    - Correspondence, circa 1980-2000; includes cards, letters and invitations. (Box-folder 1.4-1.8)
    - Date books, 1936-1937, 1944-1948, 1999, 2001 (Box-folder 1.9)
    - Diary, 1945-1947, circa 1966, 1999, undated; includes poetry, wedding invitation, garden schema, Vreelandt Lyman, Jr., Helen Lyman's "The House of the Turtle" essay., (disbound notebook) (Box-folder 1.10-1.12)
    - European art tour, 1965 (Box-folder 1.13)
    - Legal documents, 1960, 1974, 1979, 1984, 1995-1999; includes, lawsuit, 1995-1997, insurance, 1999, international driving permit, passport, deeds. (Box-folder 1.14-1.16)
    - Portraits, circa 1990 (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Short story draft (untitled), undated (Box-folder 2.2-2.3)
    - "The House of the Turtle," circa 1989, 1990 (?); includes garden. (Box-folder 2.4)
    - Travels to India, undated (Box-folder 2.5)
    - Curriculum vitae, circa 1980 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - Autobiography, 1990, 1999-2002, I.B
    - Taped interviews, 1979; includes cassette tapes: "Helen Modra to Helen Lyman," "Professor Helen Lyman interviewed on 6PR by David Hawkes," "Professor Helen Lyman interviewed on W.A.I.T. HERE radio 6NR." Also includes copies of the two latter interviews on CD-R made for University Archives online exhibit, Women's Work: a tribute to the women who make UB work, September 2004: http://ublib.buffalo.edu/libraries/units/archives/womens_work/index.htm (Box-folder 33.14)
    - Helen Lyman's life events: card file, undated (Box-folder 2.7)
    - "My Life,": notes for autobiography, 1990, undated (disbound notebook) (Box-folder 2.8)
    - General notes for autobiography, 1999-circa 2002, undated (Box-folder 2.9-2.11)
  - Family/Genealogy, I.C
    - Huguenor family, 1970, 1974, 2001, undated; includes Mann and Cotton families. (Box-folder 2.12)
    - Other family genealogical research, 1891, 1977, 1995, undated; includes Huguenin, Huguenot, Hamilton family trees, correspondence. (Box-folder 2.13-2.14)
    - Robert Hamilton Stamps, 1979-1980, undated (Box-folder 2.15)
    - Leon C. Huguenor: "Western Trip Record," undated (Box-folder 2.16)
    - Genealogical research (places), 1978, 1983, 1995, 2001, undated (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Education, I.D
    - Lockport High School (class of 1926), 50th reunion, 1976 (Box-folder 3.2)
    - University of Buffalo (class of 1932), 1982; includes photograph. (Box-folder 3.3)
    - University of Chicago, 1953, 1956; includes application, essay. (Box-folder 3.4)
    - University of Chicago: Adult education courses, 1955-1956 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 3.5-3.11)
  - Friends, I.E
    - Olive L. Ralston, medical librarian at Roswell Park, Buffalo, circa 1890, 1902, circa 1955-circa 1970, undated; includes certificates, correspondence, last will and testament, family records. (Box-folder 3.12)
    - John T. Foster, circa 1980-1989, 1995-1996, undated; includes, correspondence, family histories, autobiography, writings. (Box-folder 3.13-3.16)
    - Clipping and photographs, 1987, undated; includes George S. Ralston's hospital certificate and Felix Pollack obituary. (Box-folder 3.17)
- Professional, II.
  - Correspondence, 1978-1988, 1994-1999, undated; includes Ursula Meyer, Director of Library Services, Stockton Public Library. (Box-folder 4.1-4.3)
  - University of Wisconsin-Madison Library School Women's Group and Wisconsin Women Library Workers, 1976, 1981, 1985; includes roundtable oral history transcript of interview of Ruth Shapiro with Margaret E. Monroe, Helen Lyman and Ruth Warncke, 1976, A Biographical-Bibliographical Directory of Women Librarians by Cynthia S. Cummings, 1976, Out of the Stacks: Notable Wisconsin Women Librarians by Valmai Kirkham Fenster. (Box-folder 30.10-30.11)
  - American Library Association (ALA), II.A
    - Survey of Adult Education in Public Libraries and State Library Extensions Agencies of the United States, 1952-1953; includes notes, correspondence, speeches, comments. (Box-folder 4.4-4.9)
    - Adult Services Division Newsletter, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 4.10-4.11)
    - NEH oral history proposal, 1981 (Box-folder 4.12)
  - Buffalo Public Library, II.B
    - Annual reports: general, 1931-1937, 1942-1955; includes correspondence, notes. (Box-folder 5.1)
    - Annual reports: Reader's Bureau, 1936-1943; includes notes. (Box-folder 5.2)
    - Annual reports: Group Work program, 1945-1949, undated; includes notes. (Box-folder 5.3)
    - Annual reports: Great Books program, 1946, 1950, 1983, 1987; includes clippings, photographs, essay: "Great Books and Big Ideas" by John T. Foster, 1983. (Box-folder 5.4)
    - Annual reports: Discussion Group, 1948-1952, undated; includes pamphlets, flyers, notes, "Book Talks." (Box-folder 5.5-5.7)
    - Annual reports: Adult Education Department, 1950-1955, undated; includes, annual reports, newsletters, photographs. (Box-folder 5.8)
  - Conferences / Workshops, II.C
    - "Proceedings of the Eighth Institute on Public Library Management: Public Library - Public School Relationship," Wisconsin Free Library Commission, Feb. 26-28, 1961 (Box-folder 34.1)
    - "Preparing Librarians for Reading Guidance," ALA, Adult Education Division, University of Wisconsin Library School, Madison, WI, 1965 (Box-folder 5.9-5.10)
    - "Film and the Library: an Institute for Training in Librarianship," University of Wisconsin-Madison Library School, 1969; includes grant, schedule of events, final report. (Box-folder 34.2-34.4)
    - "Film and the Library: an Institute for Training in Librarianship": 16mm film, "The Making of a Film," Seminar IV, 1969 (Box-folder 34.5)
    - Annual conference, Adult Education Association of Wisconsin, Oshkosh, WI, 1969 (Box-folder 5.11)
    - "The Adult New Reader and His Reading," University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI, May, 1973; includes correspondence, notes, final report. (Box-folder 18.5-18.7)
    - Appalachian Adult Education Center (AAEC) Meeting, Cincinnati, OH, 1974; includes contract for consultant work. (Box-folder 18.8)
    - "Adult Basic Education and Public Library Service": proceedings, State Library of Florida, Miami Springs, FL, 1974 (Box-folder 5.12)
    - "National Conference on Adult Literacy," National Institute for Advanced Studies, 1976 (Box-folder 5.13)
    - "The Information Society Discussion," ALA, Detroit, MI, June 1977 (Box-folder 6.1)
    - "Centenary Conference," The Library Association, London, England, 1977 (Box-folder 6.2-6.5)
    - "Pre- White House Conference on Libraries," Library-Information Connection, Indianapolis, IN, Aug. 11-13, 1978 (Box-folder 6.6)
    - "Literary Conference, Bloomington Session," ALA/OLSD, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 6.7)
    - White House Conference on Libraries and Information Services, Reston, VA, Apr. 1979 (Box-folder 6.8-6.12)
    - "20th Biennial Conference," Library Association of Australia, Canberra, Australia, Aug. 1979[3 folders] (Box-folder 6.13-7.1)
    - "Lifelong Learning for Self-sufficiency," White House Conference on Aging, Racine, WI, 1980 (Box-folder 7.2)
    - "79th Annual Conference," Ontario Library Association, Toronto, ON, 1981 (Box-folder 7.3)
    - Annual conference, ALA, San Francisco, CA, 1981 (Box-folder 7.4-7.5)
    - "Literacy Conference," ALA/OLOS, PLA, Washington, DC, 1981; includes pre-conference planning. (Box-folder 7.6)
    - "Adult Core Skills," New York State Education Department, Albany, NY, 1981 (Box-folder 7.7)
    - Evaluation Report for Literacy-in-Libraries Workshop, ALA Office for Library Outreach Services, 1982 (Box-folder 18.9)
    - "Statewide Literacy Coordination Planning Conference," Kentucky Department for Libraries and Archives, Louisville, KY, 1982 (Box-folder 7.8-7.10)
    - Annual conference, New York Library Association, Buffalo, NY, 1983 (Box-folder 7.11-7.12)
    - "The Literacy Connection," Literacy Volunteers of America Inc., Albany NY, Oct. 1983 (Box-folder 18.10)
    - Pre-conference workshop, ALA, Denton, TX, 1983-1985; includes correspondence. [4 folders] (Box-folder 7.13-8.1)
    - White House Conference on Library and Information Services, 1984 (Box-folder 8.2-8.4)
    - Arrowhead Library System, "Libraries and Literacy," Janesville, WI, 1984 (Box-folder 8.5-8.7)
    - Literacy conference on the aging, State Library of Iowa, Des Moines, IA 1986 (Box-folder 8.8)
    - "Renew the Excitement - The Wisconsin Experience," T.V. General Educational Development (GED), video conference overview, WI, 1988 (Box-folder 18.11)
    - "Readers Advisory: Adult Services Workshop," The Queens Borough Public Library, Jamaica, NY Apr., 1989 (Box-folder 18.12)
    - "Library Resources and Responsibilities for the Adult New Reader: Library Literacy Workshop," South Carolina Literacy Association, Columbia, SC, May, 1989 (Box-folder 18.13)
    - "Family Literacy Fair," Bell Atlantic/ALA, Washington, D.C., Apr. 1990 (Box-folder 18.14)
    - "State Literacy Conference," Library of Michigan, et. al., Lansing, MI, 1990 (Box-folder 8.9-8.10)
    - White House Conference on Library and Information Services, Jul. 1991 (Box-folder 18.15)
    - Title VI Literacy Evaluation workshop, LSCA, Liverpool, NY, Sep. 1991 (Box-folder 18.16)
  - Publications and writings, II.D
    see also "Series IV. Adult Literacy Resources" for more research and notes
    - Correspondence, 1975, 1982-1987, 1990, undated; includes Oryx Press. (Box-folder 8.11)
    - "Personnel and Training Needs for New Responsibilities in Adult Education," typewritten draft, circa 1950 (Box-folder 8.12)
    - "Adult Education Activities in Public Libraries," published handbook, 1954 [See also: #30.7 Serials: issues on adult education/literacy, 1954-1994 - Adult Education, vol. v, no3, Spring 1955 for article by the same name.] (Box-folder 8.13)
    - "Adult Education Activities in Public Libraries," photocopy of typewritten draft, 1954 (Box-folder 9.1-9.4)
      [Original FRAGILE draft removed to 35.1-35.3]
    - "Reading and the Adult New Reader," edited typewritten draft, 1960 (Box-folder 9.5-9.12)
    - "Program Suggestions: Using the Library," column co-written with Ruth P. Swenson for Wisconsin Library Bulletin, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 9.13)
    - "Reading for an Age of Change: A Handbook for Librarians," 1963 (Box-folder 9.14)
    - Speeches, 1967-1971; includes "New and Continuing Areas of Concern in Adult Services," 1968, "The Library Reading Program for the Adult New Reader," 1971, correspondence. (Box-folder 9.15)
    - Library Trends: Library Programs and Services to the Disadvantaged, vol. 20, no. 2: issue editor, Oct. 1971 (Box-folder 10.1)
    - "Reading and the New Adult Reader," published in Library Trends, vol. 22, no. 2, October, 1973 (Box-folder 10.2)
    - "Adult Reading and the New Adult Reader," typewritten essay, 1975 (Box-folder 10.3)
    - Reading and the New Adult Reader, (two versions), galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 10.4-10.6)
    - Literacy and the Nation's Libraries, typewritten draft, 1976 (Box-folder 10.7-10.10)
    - Literacy and the Nation's Libraries, galley proof, 1977[5 folders] (Box-folder 10.11-11.3)
    - "Frank A. Hutchins Biography," published in Dictionary of American Library Biography, 1975-1978; includes correspondence, drafts, and notes. (Box-folder 11.4)
    - "Learning to Read," published in International Altrusan, vol. 55, no.8, April 1978; includes typewritten draft, correspondence. (Box-folder 11.5)
    - "Literacy Education as Library Community Service," published in Library Trends: Emerging Patterns of Community Service, Fall 1979; includes correspondence, 1978-1979. (Box-folder 11.6)
    - Literacy Volunteers of America, Inc., evaluation reports for "Bibliography of Humanistic Reading," "Development of Adult Low Level Reading Materials," 1979-1980 (Box-folder 11.7)
    - Opening Doors for New Adult Readers, by Linda Bayley, (preface by Lyman), 1980 (Box-folder 11.8)
    - "Literacy Programs, Library," published in ALA Yearbook, 1982; includes typewritten draft, correspondence. (Box-folder 11.9)
    - "Reflections on Library Literacy Efforts," published in Louisiana Library Association (LLA) Bulletin, vol. 45, no. 1, Summer 1982 (Box-folder 11.10)
    - Book review: "Reading, Research, and Librarianship: A History and Analysis," by Stephen Karetzky, published in Journal of Library History, 1983; includes correspondence. (Box-folder 11.11)
    - "Libraries and Literacy Education: Looking Forward," published in Public Libraries, vol. 23, no. 4, Winter 1984; includes typewritten draft, notes. (Box-folder 11.12)
    - "Libraries and Adult Literacy Education in Wisconsin: 1965-1984," published in Wisconsin Library Bulletin, Winter 1984 (Box-folder 11.13)
    - "Literacy and Library Collection Development" proposal, 1985-1986; includes typewritten essay co-written with Debra Wilcox Johnson. (Box-folder 11.14)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: proposal, 1985, 1991, undated; includes correspondence. (Box-folder 12.1-12.2)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: general notes, undated (Box-folder 12.3-12.4)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: contents notes, undated (Box-folder 12.5-12.6)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: preface notes, undated (Box-folder 12.7)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 1: Introduction," notes, undated (Box-folder 12.8-12.9)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 2: Adult, Adult Development and Learning," notes, 1981, undated (Box-folder 12.10)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 3: Adult Services defined by Practice and Field Research," notes, undated (Box-folder 12.11)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 4: Assets: Foundation for Adult Services," notes, undated (Box-folder 12.12)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 5: Services and Strategies Programs," 1985, 1990-1991; includes research, notes, "Reader's Advisory Workshop ALA Chicago," "Jeannie Flexner and the Reader's Advisory," by Renee Feinberg, 1990, undated (Box-folder 13.1-13.3)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 6 - Programs, Activities and Strategies," notes, 1986, undated (Box-folder 13.4)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Part 7 - Issues and Resolutions, Challenges and Concerns," notes, 1995, undated (Box-folder 13.5)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Adult Services and Resources," notes, July, 1988 (Box-folder 13.6)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: "Examples Programs," 1991, undated (Box-folder 13.7)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: research, 1962-1963, 1996; includes Reference Services in a Small Public Library, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 13.8)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: Adult Services Workshop #2, October, 1988 (Box-folder 13.9)
    - Adult Services: Vision and Performance: bibliography, notes, 1982, undated (Box-folder 13.10)
    - "Literacy Education and Libraries," notes, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13.11-13.13)
    - Notes for Perspective on Aging, 1986; includes correspondence. (Box-folder 13.14)
    - Notes for unpublished Library Trends article, October 1986 (Box-folder 13.15)
    - "Background Paper for The State Library of Iowa Literacy Project," typewritten draft, 1986-1987; includes correspondence. (Box-folder 14.1)
    - "Libraries, Literacy, and the Information Society," 1990; includes typewritten draft, correspondence. (Box-folder 14.2)
    - School of Information and Library Studies, University at Buffalo, commencement speech, May 1991; includes typewritten speech, publications and correspondence. [removed from folder 13.8] (Box-folder 14.3)
    - "Talk to LIS 505 class at Erie County Community College," notes, 1996; includes correspondence. (Box-folder 14.4)
    - Book reviews, 1973-1974, 1976-1979, undated (Box-folder 14.5)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Office of Education, Office of Libraries and Learning Technologies, II.E
    - "Review of Data-Gathering Instruments," 1963, 1965-1969, undated; includes correspondence, notes. (Box-folder 14.6)
    - Library Materials Research Project (LMRP) project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," proposal, 1967-1972 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 14.7-14.10)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," progress report, 1967, 1969; includes LMRP Population Study. (disbound binder) (Box-folder 14.11-14.14)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," progress report, 1970-1971 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 15.1-15.3)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," Materials Analysis Criteria (MAC) checklist, 1969-1971 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 15.4-15.7)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, Population Study, background research, 1971, undated (disbound binder) (Box-folder 15.8-15.11)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," final report, Oct. 1968 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 15.12)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," interim report, 1970(disbound binder) (Box-folder 16.1-16.2)
    - LMRP project 7-1220, "Library Materials in Service to the Adult New Reader," final report 1972; includes introduction, parts 1-6, appendix 1-10, and withdrawn tables. [13 folders] (Box-folder 16.3-17.1)
    - Project 2-0413, "Knowledge/Information Needs of the Disadvantaged," by Thomas Childers, Oct. 1973 (Box-folder 17.2-17.3)
    - Project RO 2-0560, "Project Rapskills: Cooperative Planning to Maximize Adult Basic Education Opportunities Through Public Library Extensions in Appalachian North Carolina," by Maryelee F. Newman, Oct., 1975 (Box-folder 17.4-17.6)